Let's create the project charter.
So we talked about the ITTOs and we did
cover this at a high level.
Let's go into more depth.
So the purpose of the
project charter, formal
authorization for the project to begin.
Remember in the PMI world, we do not have
a project till we have a project charter.
So it will show the business justification
of the project, why the project exists.
So we will definitely list the need for
the project.
Outlines the project's measurable
objectives, related success criteria.
This is at a high level.
This is a high level document signed off.
They might say published by the project
sponsor or initiator.
So it identifies the sponsor
who is funding the project
and the project manager
and their authority levels.
It contains high level requirements,
scope, risk, summary budget.
budget, summary schedule.
Those are high level.
High level assumptions and constraints we
already know about.
Pre-assigned resources meaning promised
resources, team, people,
and physical resources.
Documents any key stakeholders identified,
identifies who will approve the
deliverables, summary milestone and exit
criteria.
So the PM's role in creating the project
charter.
They can assist in
writing the project charter
or the PM can write
the entire project charter.
If you're a senior level
project manager, we're
often being asked to
write the project charter.
But the sponsor or initiator will sign it.
And we'll do a benefits evaluation.
Is the project in line with the
organization's strategic plan?
So that is our job to make sure it is.
We'll communicate.
communicate to the appropriate
key stakeholders, letting
them know we've got a
project authorized to begin.
So the project charter also be called an
overview statement.
It's an executive summary of the project
charter.
Elevator pitch communicates the intent and
vision of the project
must be clear and concise.
But note, I'm going to read this.
Authorization of the project
starts when the project charter
is signed or the project
overview statement is approved.
Then the PM can start spending
money on the project and
obtaining resources to actually
accomplish project objectives.